all right so this will be a bit of a
break up from that from the conversation
but it is something I want to ask you
because I think it's that valuable that
I want people to hear it and it's the
distinction you make between the having
mode and having needs and the being mode
and being needs for yeah this is one
where look I have a guy that comes along
to the meetup and watches this with me
very very smart guy very well educated
he works in some sort of psychological
capacity with people who have various
problems and he takes transformation
seriously from every level of analysis
physiological psychological spiritual
but even this distinction for him I
think was like a light bulb moment in
terms of well it's such a simple way to
articulate something so fundamental
about what we are that speaks
importantly to where we are often going
wrong in current culture so if you would
please the having mode and the being
mode I'd love for you to tell us about
that
thank you so the idea is drawn from
Erich Fromm his book you know to heaven
to be but and and Fromm is clear about
this he doesn't think he's the
originator of this distinction you can
find analogous distinctions in in many
places
Steven Bachelor has a version of this
distinction in his book alone with
others an existential interpretation of
Buddhism you can find something an
allegation Gabriel Marcel so right and I
think even you could understand parts of
what Heidegger is doing using this
distinction but I think Fromm and the
reason why I use from ways of talking
about it although I supplement it a bit
with with Boober and with Collingwood
right I think that it's a very clear and
concise way of talking about it
so Fromm's idea is that right first of
all we have to get this notion of an
existential mode right so when I'm
talking about an existential mode I'm
talking about this process of Co
identification right I'm always assuming
a particular identity in order to
exercise my agency and I'm projecting
onto the world I set set of identities
in order to make that world an
intelligible arena for my action and so
those and this is also related to you
know clifford geertz his work on
worldviews right but that that deep
participatory relationship the way they
Co define and co-create each other yes
okay that's the existential mode and
that what Fromm was pointing out is we
have two fundamentally different
existential modes and these modes these
agent arena Co fitting relationships are
organized around different sets of needs
we have and so they're having needs our
needs that are met by having things
exercising control over them ultimately
often ultimately consuming them like
oxygen food water or at least having
really intimate control over them like
shelter etc right and then Fromm's
notion is well those are first of all
neither mode is right or wrong okay yes
but the having mode is right it's a
legitimate mode because we do have these
needs there's things we literally have
to consume and have power and control
over or we cease to be yes and then he
asked a really good question like what
like what is your cognitive machinery
like right and what's your existential
mode like in order to facilitate solving
this we says well what you do is you and
here I'll use some Collingwood ideas to
make it a little bit clearer but what I
do is I give things a categorical
identity like this is a glass right and
so III can quickly and efficiently know
know how to get control over it and
manipulate it because I can put it into
a category and I can use the way in
which it's similar to all the other
glasses and the way I could replace this
with another glass so all of that
ability sign a categorical identity and
then that tells you what my relationship
is to it my relationship is one of you
know what Fromm calls like animal
intelligence that that that's not an
insult by the way right it means my
tremendous capacity to manipulate things
in the world in order to write to solve
my having needs so I have an i it
relationships of things to use an idea
from Boober
now then Fromm pointed out but we have a
different set of needs he calls them
being needs I sometimes think that it
might be more accurate to call them
becoming needs or developmental needs
so we have a need to be mature we need
to we have a need to become mature to
develop maturity we have a need to you
know become virtuous we need to you know
we have a need to become authentic these
are these are things we need to become
so these are not these needs are not met
by controlling or manipulating these are
needs that are met through and this goes
back to something we were talking about
not that long ago these needs are met by
going through important developmental
transformations yes in in really
important ways coming up with ways in
which we overcome that existential
inertia that that existential ignorant
and fundamentally go through a process
of self transcendence and so the being
needs are met
therefore by a different framework of
cognition because now I'm not primarily
trying to solve problems in the sense of
come up with an answer of how to quickly
get my goal instead what I'm trying to
do is connect myself to reality like to
the reality of who I am and the reality
out there so that I can get this
reciprocal realization so that I and the
world can Co transform the agent in the
arena can Co transform so that I become
a different you know cognitive agent so
my relationship now is not one of animal
intelligence it's one of reflect
reflective reason where reason is this
process by which we take ourselves so
when I use reason I'm not talking about
syllogistic argumentation I'm talking
about this process by which we put
ourselves through like development in
order to enhance and optimize our
capacities with respect to the world so
because I'm engaged in this project
right of making meaning because that's
what reason is doing for me mate right
and and going through this developmental
change I don't have an i it relationship
to things I want to be connected to
things so that I can penetrate to their
mystery right and and and the mystery
that that's still within me see the
mystery is that is that developmental of
ordinance right for these kinds of
transformations and self transcendence
that are needed for the being mode so
have an i though relationship yeah to
use Buber a my my interaction with
things is not categorically but
expressively so I'll often use the this
point right presumably and this is and I
think I share this with people that's my
presumption your relationship to a deep
friend or your romantic partner is a
developmental relationship of reciprocal
realization you're both you're both
affording each other's growth and and
and and disclosure of depth both within
yourself and within the arena of your
life right and so your relationship to
your partner or to your deep friend is
not an I it categorical manipulative
relationship I wouldn't say to my
partner I wouldn't say to her you know
I'm with you because you remind me so
readily of all the other women I've ever
been with like that gives me information
so that I can efficiently and
effectively manipulate you and control
you in order to you know service my
needs like that is not making this
relationship go well I'm destroying the
relationship because that is not why she
has entered into this relationship right
she's not entered into it to solve a
problem to have control over resources
she's entered into it to become a
different person and that is of course
why I've also entered into it so here's
the issue then both modes are legitimate
what from and I would argue and this is
what Stephen Bachelor argues you know
what Buddhism and many things are
talking about is modal confusion when we
confuse when we pursue right we use the
wrong mode to pursue the needs were
pursuing and the classic example that
Fromm uses is we pursue the being needs
from within the having mode so that you
know in order to become mature we have a
car in order to be in love we have lots
of sex right right and and and so what
we can proms point right is that
confusion serves other people in their
capacity to exploit and manipulate us
because if I can keep
you trapped in the having mode you are
of course we are being frustrated and I
mean at an a deep existential and
psychological sense you're being
frustrated in your attempt to satisfy
your being needs so you what would you
do you're trapped in the having mode and
having the car isn't doing it so it must
mean that I don't have the right car or
I've got to get a new car or a new
iPhone or right or I've got to get more
likes I have to have more likes on my
social media and so you pursue this with
an increasing frenzy and then Fromm
predicts there's two responses to that
like the the the the futility and the
frustration bifurcate and you either
fall into a kind of deep despair or you
that that frustration and futility
reaches out in the only way in which you
feel you can again reconnect to reality
which is sort of a violent you know
reaction anger and you know attacking
those around you because that's sort of
the last resort you have to at least
reconnect to reality in some fundamental
way
so the modal confusion is a profound way
in which we can be deceived and and and
that deception also makes us X you know
quite exceptionally vulnerable to to
manipulation by others beautiful thank
you very much for taking us through that
I think it's incredibly valuable